Welcome back to A Push in Under 3
Minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. America, a beautiful country of
glorious cities, but there's really only
one place you can call perfect. That's
right, the American South. So, what was
the South like in this time period?
Well, first off, geography and the
environment shaped the South's economy
and identity. Southern land was perfect
for growing cash crops like cotton,
tobacco, and sugar, but there was also a
problem, overcultivation. The soil of
the Southeast became depleted, so
slaveholders moved west, exploiting
plantations into new fertile land in
places like Alabama, Mississippi, and
Texas. All right, enough beating around
the bush. So, slavery. Although most
Southerners didn't own enslaved people,
the region's economy and leadership were
built on slavery. Southern leaders like
John C. Calhoun went from calling
slavery a necessary evil to defending it
as a positive good. According to
Calhoun, slavery wasn't just acceptable,
it was essential to the Southern way of
life. This focus on agriculture and
slavery gave the South a distinct
regional identity. While the North
industrialized and diversified, the
South stayed locked in traditional
agriculture staples and resisted change.
Southern business leaders kept relying
on cotton exports to drive their
economy, which made the South heavily
dependent on both slavery and foreign
trade. So, what to take away from this
is the South became its kind of own
place and culture during this time
period, and this tension with the North
would, wait, say it with me, cause a
future war. On the screen now are some
AP style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers up now.
I will see you in the next one.